Okay, and to start with, as usual, we're going to go into our code folder on our desktop
here and we are going to copy our template and we're going to go ahead and paste the item.
If you're not familiar with the template, it will be linked within the course.
It is also available on my GitHub and we have just basic HTML, CSS, and JavaScript files
inside of our template.
Okay, so I'm going to rename this to be typing -test and I'm going to press enter.
I can close this and I'm going to go ahead and open Visual Studio Code.
And in our Explorer, we're going to open a folder and we're going to open our typing
test folder.
Okay, so we'll start with our index HTML, actually I'll open everything here and you'll
see our script.js has nothing in it.
Our style CSS has some very basic styling and then our index HTML here.
We can actually remove a couple things.
I'll actually maybe close that for now.
We can remove this to grab a custom favicon.
We do have a favicon as well included in our template and we'll maybe change our title
here to be typing test and we're actually not using font awesome, so I'm going to go ahead
and get rid of that out.
Well, okay, and we can use our live server, which is a very handy Visual Studio Code extension
and you'll see that we have our project here and we have typing test and we have our
hello world.
So let's go back and start making our UI here.
So the goal of this video is to just make the main UI.
So we're going to start out with an h1 and this is just going to say typing test and then
from there we're going to create a div with an ID, so div hash text dash container and
press tab and that's going to create our div with the ID text container.
And then below that we're going to create another div with the ID of timer and this is
going to be for our timer.
I'm just going to write inside here time left 60 s, okay.
And then we will have a div hash tag final dash score and this will be for our final
score, of course, when we're done typing and then we'll also have a button and this will
be of type button and this is going to have an ID of try dash again and this is going
to be our try again button.
So that is it for our HTML, very, very straightforward.
So let's dive into our styling a bit.
We can actually maybe check it out, it's not going to look like much.
So we have a h1, we have a div with some text and then we have a try again button, okay.
So let's make it look a little bit better than that.
All right.
So for our body, we are going to want to have a margin of zero, we'll say that it'll
just be a height of 100, the h and then we're going to have a background of white smoke.
Feel free to change up your background colors or any other type of creative background you
would like.
You could use a hero pattern background, video background, gradient background, there's lots
of options, but I'm going to keep it very minimal and very simple.
Next we want to make sure we have an overflow hidden.
So we don't want to be able to scroll in any direction for our body.
And then we're going to use flex box, so display flex.
And we're going to do a flex direction of column so that everything is going top to bottom.
Simplify content center and align items center to center things at both vertically and
horizontal lead.
And then lastly, our font family is going to be mono space.
So mono space is important in this case because it means that every character is going
to take up the same width.
So that is going to be important later on and we'll get more into that when we get into
the functionality.
And then the font size, I'm going to make 1.5 REM.
Okay, so let's go ahead and check that out.
All right, so that already looks a lot better and it looks reasonably close to our final
product here.
We are going to need to style the button.
And you can see that we do not actually see our text container yet.
So let's go ahead and work on our text container.
Okay, so we'll just target our hashtag #text-container.
And inside of this, we'll start with a width of 800 pixels and we're going to give it
a height auto and scroll down a bit and we're going to give it a margin, 20 pixels top
and bottom and left and right auto.
And we are going to give it a line height of to REM.
We're going to give it a little bit of space, be under 1.5 REM and white space, no wrap.
We're going to give it a background white, padding, 10 pixels all the way around, border
dash radius of 5 pixels, overflow is also going to be hidden inside of this.
And then we're going to use display flex, a line item center.
We want to align everything vertically in our container and we're going to use a position
relative and a cursor of none so that when we're typing, we're just focused on the
typing.
And you know what, let's actually put some text in here.
This is our text, okay and let's go back and check that out.
Okay, so again, looking good, if I hover into it, you'll see that my cursor is disappearing.
That's going to help us focus a little bit better on our text here, okay, nice from there.
Our timer text could be a little bit smaller and maybe we want more of a margin around
there.
So let's go ahead and address that timer.
Let's give it a margin, 10 pixels all the way around and a font size of 1.2 REM.
Okay, let's check that.
Okay, that's looking better.
Some nice spacing there.
Now we're going to need to style our button here, so we'll just style our button element
itself.
We'll give that a padding, 10 pixels, give it a width of 150 pixels.
We're going to give it a background color.
Again, you can choose whatever color you would like.
This is what I used in my version of the project, and we'll give it a color of white, border,
radius, make it eight pixels, a little bit more rounded, border, none.
So by default, buttons have an inset border that I don't think looks overly good, so I usually
get rid of it.
Curse our pointer, show the user that it can be clicked on, and we'll give it a margin
top of 20 pixels, and again, we want a font size of 1.2 REM, so make the font size a little
bit bigger than it is by default, and let's check that out.
Okay, that's looking good.
Next, we want a hover effect of some kind when we hover over our button, so button, pseudo
class hover, and I'm going to use, again, my filter brightness trick, and I'll set the value
to 1.2, so this will work no matter what your color is.
You can see that it's just making everything get a little bit lighter, it's 20% brighter,
I should say, and yeah, that's how I like to do it.
It does work regardless of the color, unless your color is already very, very bright,
like if you add a white background, it doesn't work as well, of course, okay, and then
we need a green and red for our correct and incorrect letter colors, and that's pretty
straightforward.
We'll make a class called correct, and I'm just going to have the color be green, and
then we'll make another class called error, and that color is going to be red.
Okay, and then lastly, we do want to hide our button for now, it's going to pop up later
on once we're actually done.
Okay, and that is literally it for our UI, very minimalist, as I said, and the big part
of this project is going to be the functionality, and we'll be tackling that in the next
one.
I'll see you then. Bye for now.